MY COPSA MICAS

Dan Simmons

1.

I was driving through the mountains of Transylvania in search of the historical Dracula when I encountered Copsa Mica. The town’s name is pronounced Cope-sha Mee-ka and I had heard of it before coming to Romania—I had even written about it in the short story that had ballooned to a novel and sent me to this cold, remote region to do research—but the impact of the actual place was greater than I had expected.

Copsa Mica had received some small space in the western press as “the most polluted place in the world.” The town of some seven thousand people, little more than a village, is dominated by the massive Carbosin plant that makes carbon black for the production of tires. The Carbosin plant and a nearby lead factory employ almost all of the people in Copsa Mica, fill half the valley with their bleak industrial buildings, and rain carbon black on landscape and humans alike. The filth and pollution were the legacy of the late and unlamented Nicolae Ceausescu.

I had not planned to visit Copsa Mica—its role in my story and novel was tangential at most—but our drive from the city of Sibiu to the town of Sighişoara, birthplace of Vlad Dracula, passed through the small industrial town. I say “our drive” because I was traveling with my sister-in-law. She had been born in Germany but had lived in the States since she was sixteen. The theory behind her traveling with me during this research swing through Romania was that although this region of Transylvania had not been a Saxon-dominated area for five centuries or more, the people would still speak German and we would not require the usual Office of National Tourism “guide” who also served as informer to the Securitate secret police.

The theory worked. We drove the rattling, rental Dacia through the Transylvania Alps for a week, communicating with waiters, officials, museum directors, and ordinary people via our smattering of Romanian and my sister-in-law’s German. And then, on a cold, drizzly Monday morning in May, we left the mountain town of Sibiu for the ever-more-mountainous town of Sighişoara and encountered Copsa Mica.

We saw the smoke first. Romania is littered with industrial towns—the air in the refinery city of Pitesti had been so foul that we had rolled up the Dacia’s windows and still ended up coughing and wheezing for an hour beyond the city limits—but the smoke above Copsa Mica seemed almost solid, a black fog bank suspended between the hills and above the city like a low ceiling of slowly bubbling asphalt. We were already beneath that black cloud when we came over the last rise and entered Copsa Mica itself.

The kilometer-marker stones were black. One could just make out the town’s name on a tombstone-like slab as we entered the edge of the village. The houses were black. The painted wood fences were black. The stones of the sidewalks were covered with an ash-thin film of black; the sheets hanging on the lines to dry were gray. Sheep being driven along the roadside by two young boys were black, although one could catch a glimpse of grayish-white wool in the places where the boys’ sticks had touched the backs of the sheep. The boys looked like young Gypsies with black hair, black clothes, and lines of black grime in the creases of their necks and cheeks. Billions of ashsized carbon particles blew from west to east above the village, the smoke reminding me of the deadly black fog used by the Martian war machines in H.G. Wells’ The War of the Worlds.

The road swung northeast in the center of Copsa Mica, away from the larger factories and back into the countryside where foothills rose to real mountains swathed in clouds of a cleaner shade of gray. My sister-in-law had brought her camera; I had only a sketchbook. It had begun to rain again. The Dacia’s one working wiper smeared black smudge back and forth on the windshield. I drove back down the single paved road of the town again, hunting for a vantage point where we could take a photo. When we stopped to turn around across from the factory entrance near a clutter of empty crates that may have been an open marketplace, a crowd of Gypsy women and children rushed the car, hands groping for chewing gum that my sister-in-law had offered the first boy to approach. The old woman sitting behind crates, their faces streaked black beneath black hair under black scarves, shoved the grasping children aside in their own eagerness to grab at gum or whatever we would offer.

I turned the Dacia around and headed east again, turning left onto a cinder alley between pre-war factory buildings. Just before the narrow road wound into a maze of slag heaps and brick warehouses, there was a small rise with a view of the town, the smokestacks, and the carbon black factory. I pulled into a cinder turn-out and said, ‘This should do it. Let’s shoot a couple of photos.”

It should be understood that I knew that we were breaking the law. All “strategic areas” are off-limits to photography in Romania. Every factory is a strategic area. It didn’t matter that this carbon-black factory had been photographed and filmed ad nauseum since the fall of the Ceausescu regime as an example of Eastern European pollution at its worst; it did not matter that Ceausescu’s police state had been theoretically buried with the man and his wife. This was a factory. Factories were State property. State property was off-limits to all photography, but especially to foreigners’ photography.

My sister-in-law stepped away from the car and composed the shot with maddening slowness. I didn’t want artistry. I wanted one we-were-here, I’ve-documented-it-for-posterity snapshot of the filthiest town on earth. Then I wanted to get on with finding Dracula’s birthplace in Sighişoara, still a three-hour drive through the mountains.

She checked the composition through her viewfinder, found it lacking, moved away from the Dacia, checked it again, frowned, and fiddled with the settings on the long lens.

A heavy truck came up the road out of the slag heaps. I could see three Romanian soldiers in the front seat. There may have been more under the tarp behind the cab.

“Lower the camera,” I said through the open window. The drizzle had stopped.

My sister-in-law stood there, camera still raised. The soldiers were pointing at her and talking animatedly.

I said softly, “Lower the camera.” It was too late to hide our effort at photography, but there was no need to provoke these clowns. The roll of film in her Minolta held not only the photos I needed of Sibiu, but the documentation of Castle Dracula two hundred miles and a maze of mountains behind us. I nose photos were half the reason I had flown to Romania. “Let’s go,” I said.

She did not lower the camera. The truck had slammed to a stop now and the soldier on the far side swung out on a running board. The driver was waving his hand at her. The soldier on the running board had a small machine-gun, something like the old Sten guns one sees in World War II movies, slung over his shoulder. He shifted it on his hip as he began to shout at us.

My sister-in-law did not lower the camera but she smiled at them. Her theory whenever encountering Romanian officialdom at its most Gestapoish was to give them a big smile.

The soldiers were not beguiled. The one on the running board swung down from the truck. The driver opened his door and shook his fist. A face peered around the canvas at the back of the truck. I had visions of sitting in a security office somewhere down in those slag heaps, waiting while Romanian military bureaucracy ground its peristaltic way toward some decision. Several times in Romania we had been through the process of having our passports taken, scrutinized, frowned over, and argued about by military-types who could obviously barely read. Now I could imagine our film being confiscated in the same methodical, emotionless process.

She continued smiling at them, her eye back at the viewfinder. The soldier was coming around the front of his truck now.

I leaned across the Dacia’s front seat, swung the passenger door open, called my sister-in-law by name, and said very quietly but very firmly, “Lower the fucking camera and get in the fucking car. Now.”

The smile disappeared. She got in the car. The soldier stopped where he was and angrily waved his arm, pointing down the road. I backed the Dacia out, found a wider place to turn around, and left the factory grounds. The truck followed us out.

My passenger brooded the rest of that day and much of the rest of the trip. She would not be party to cowardice. She was an American. She did not back down in front of penny-ante officials. She had a right to photograph whatever she wanted. I might be timid, but she was bold. Her motto was to stand her ground. Never show fear. Smiles are more powerful than guns. They’re only human.

I listened for a while and then shut it out when I realized that her bravado was the brittle courage of someone who had never been in a position of real powerlessness. She had no concept of the depth of Romanian paranoia, no understanding of how real their security mania was . . . even when it applied to a filthy old carbon black plant.

We reached Sighişoara by mid-afternoon. The birthplace of Vlad Dracula was a medieval mountain town surrounded by stone walls and towers shrouded in gray clouds. The windshield of the Dacia was still streaked with black grime as we parked and climbed the cobblestone alleys of Sighişoara. I found myself looking at the twelfth-century homes and churches but thinking of the black cloud floating above a soot-buried village hundreds of kilometers to the west. I found myself thinking of Copsa Mica.

2.

The anthology request was to write a story of ecological horror. The usual clichés came to mind: mutants wandering a despoiled landscape, roving gangs of thugs in an ozone-blistered desert ala Bladerunner or A Boy and His Dog, vicious humans drowning in their own filth while the ecosphere gasped its last. Terence, A.E. Housman said, this is stupid stuff.

I’ll wait, I thought. Wait to see what real horror might touch me. If none does, there will be no story.

3.

Madame Bovary may be the most horrific novel I have ever read. I confess I did not read it until the spring of 1991, only weeks before I was to leave for Romania.

I was in New York City for the Nebula Awards: little blocks of Lucite with galaxies of sand in them, given by the Science Fiction Writers of America. I did not belong to the organization. My novel was not destined to win.

The awards ceremony was at the Roosevelt Hotel, a rotting hulk of a place that now catered to large herds of naive foreign and domestic tourists. My room was almost precisely the size of a small storage closet we kept filled with junk in our garage back in Colorado. The walls of the room were waterstained the color of dried blood, the wallpaper was peeling at every corner, the tattered carpet was caked with great gobs of something that may have been semen, the window looked out on an alley and would not close all the way, and there came the sound of insects and rodents scrabbling inside the walls and the equally clear sound of humans mating on the other side of the inhabited walls. All in all, it was about the best one could do for a hundred-dollar room in New York in 1991.

I did not sleep at all that night. The alley outside the sagging window was some sort of central dumping depot for every garbage truck in Manhattan. First would come the grinding of gears, then the wild beeping of their backing-up alert, then a grinding of steel on concrete, then another louder grinding of gears and servomechanisms as trash was mashed, raised, and dumped into what sounded like a bottomless steel tube. This went on from midnight to six a.m. I read Madame Bovary until the first April light filtered through the grimy window. I took the paperback with me as I went out into the cold rain to find a coffeeshop open at five-thirty.

I thought as I read of the death of Emma Bovary that this might be the most perfectly horrible scene I had ever read or ever would read. But a few pages further on, there was horror beyond horrors. You probably know the scenes I mean.

“Charles came in, walked over to the bed and slowly drew back the curtains.”

“Emma’s head was turned toward her right shoulder. The corner of her mouth, which remained open, was like a black hole at the bottom of her face; both thumbs were bent inward toward the palms; her eyelashes were sprinkled with a kind of white dust; and her eyes were beginning to disappear in viscous pallor that was like a fine web, as though spiders had been spinning on her face. The sheet sagged from her breasts to her knees, rising again at the tips of her toes; and it seemed to Charles that an infinite mass, an enormous weight, was pressing down on her.”

At six o’clock in the morning, in a Greek coffeeshop in midtown Manhattan, I shoved aside my cup of coffee and leaned against the Formica counter, feeling the cold sweat of revulsion on my forehead and upper lip. This was infinitely worse than anything Skipp and Spector or any of the other so-called splatterpunk horror writers could throw at me. This was pure genius casting a totally unsentimental eye at death. Nor was it just death that rose from the pages like the scent of corruption; it was the absolute death of a character who had been more alive than many living people I knew.

I thought this was the worst. I was wrong. A page later came the worst.

“When Homais came back at nine o’clock (he seemed to have been constantly in the square for the past two days), he was laden with a supply of camphor, benzoin and aromatic herbs. He also brought a vase full of chlorine water, to drive away miasmas. When he arrived, the maid, Madame Lefrangois and the elder Madame Bovary were gathered around Emma, about to finish dressing her; they drew down the long, stiff veil which covered her all the way to her satin shoes.

“Felicite sobbed: ‘Oh, my poor mistress! My poor mistress!”

“ ‘Look at her,” said Madame Lefrangois with a sigh. “’She’s still so pretty! You’d swear she was about to get up!”

“Then they bent over and put on her wreath.

“They had to lift her head a little, and when they did so a flood of black liquid came from her mouth as though she were vomiting.

‘ “Oh! Look out for the dress!’ cried Madame Lefrangois. ‘Give us a hand!’ she said to the pharmacist. ‘You’re not afraid by any chance, are you?” ’

I don’t know about the pharmacist, but I was afraid. I left my breakfast uneaten, my coffee untouched, and went out to walk off the nausea and sickness through the rain-slick streets. There was an apartment-workers’ strike. Residents and shop owners had carried out garbage and piled it ten feet high along the curb. The stench was powerful.

It was not the first time I had realized that New York was a corpse, but it was the first time I had seen its face under the veil. The city was like Emma Bovary, its death made all the more terrible by the memory of its vital and vivacious past.

Street workers were flushing something from the sewers near the Roosevelt Hotel. Black liquid gushed from the dark hose and flowed into the garbage-strewn gutters.

4.

Where I live in Colorado, the environment does not seem so badly endangered. When we moved to the Front Range of the Rockies near Boulder in 1974, my wife and I would drive up Flagstaff Mountain and look out at the patchwork of lights running along the base of the foothills: small constellations of towns and villages connected only by the most tenuous of gleams where headlights moved along gossamer webs of highways.

Recently we had dinner with Steve King and his wife Tabitha at a restaurant halfway up Flagstaff Mountain. The carpet of lights beyond the window was almost solid as far north and south as we could see along the Front Range. Few patches of darkness remained and even those were not absolute.

“It’s changed since I lived here in the early ‘seventies,” said King. “People multiply and spread like cancer cells. It’s scary.”

I nodded agreement and turned my attention to the chocolate mousse.

5.

I know something about cancer. Both of my parents died of it, each battling it for six months during that final year of their lives.

There is a smell to terminal lung cancer. It may be due to the actual breakdown of lung tissue or to the growth of cancer there like fibrous roots filling up every free space in the sacs of the lungs. I used to sit on the edge of the hospital bed and hold my father’s shoulders as he coughed and spat up small, gray pieces of his lungs. The smell was unforgettable. It was not unlike Copsa Mica.

My father’s shoulders grew thinner and sharper and more brittle feeling until I was afraid that I would break bones if I held him too tightly as he coughed. He was only sixty years old. It had been less than two decades since he used to swing me up on his shoulders when I was a toddler; I could not imagine anyone’s shoulders being stronger, or broader, or a safer perch to rest on.

During the last weeks of my father’s life, my two brothers and I resumed the schedule of watches that we held during the last months of my mother’s losing battle with cancer. My older brother would be with Dad from morning until mid-afternoon. My younger brother would spend the afternoon and evening with him. I would stay by the bedside from eleven p.m. until eight in the morning.

A few hours before my father died, at 4:53 in the morning, after two days of what the doctors called coma, Dad sat straight up in bed, opened his eyes, looked at me, said, “Saugus,” in a strong voice that seemed to carry some warning, and then lay back, put his hands behind his head the way he used to while dozing off in front of the television, and went back to sleep for the last time.

I didn’t know then what Saugus meant. I do not know today. But a few years ago, on a lecture-trip to Boston, I got my rental car lost on a black, rainy night and found myself wandering through endless streets of rowhouses, then down twisty lanes to darkened suburbs where water dripped from soot-black trees, and finally I stopped near a road sign to find directions back to Highway 1. SAUGUS, the sign read, POP 25,110.

I did not tarry there.

6.

In Copsa Mica almost all of the children suffer from bronchitis and asthma from the carbon black, but it is not the respiratory diseases that will almost certainly kill them at a young age. They will die young from the high concentrations of lead, zinc, and cadmium in the soil.

In Chicago, the air is so rife with lead poisoning from auto emissions that children who live in apartment projects facing the highways test out with a lower I.Q. than children in projects closer to the lake. But even the children living away from the freeway continue to be brain-damaged by eating lead-based paint when they are infants. They will probably not die from lead poisoning; the children of the Chicago projects have a greater than thirty percent chance of dying of gang violence or drug abuse before they are twenty-five.

Saul Bellow once wrote a novel where he championed the hypothesis that lead and other heavy-metal poisoning is making our culture too stupid to survive. The expert quoted in the novel pointed out that Rome began its most precipitous decline after the aqueduct system was lined with lead.

I went to see Saul Bellow at the Miami Book Fair in 1990. So many people showed up for Bellow’s reading that they moved it from a university auditorium to a baroque church across the street. The story he read was brilliant and profane; it dealt with a young man’s sexual awakening in Chicago around the time of the First World War.

After the reading, I found myself locked out of the church and waiting for a ride in an alley in downtown Miami. Saul Bellow and a small entourage of culture mavens were hustled out by the Book Fair sponsors and for a second we shared the stoop at the back of the church. The car that glided up for him was a new Silhouette Van that looked like one of the photos of the Cars of the Future I used to cut out for my scrapbook when I was seven. Beyond Bellow’s wattled neck and porkpie hat, a monorail people-mover glided overhead to the center of Miami.

Farther south, a skyscraper outlined m blue neon pulsed laser beams out toward the bay.

Shit, I thought, I’ve finally made it I’m in the future.

They bundled Saul Bellow into the Silhouette Van and then I was alone in the alley. There were no cabs, no phone booths, not even a lighted convenience store for blocks in any direction. Beneath the laser pulses and monorail rumbles, the city looked bombed and blasted and as dead as Emma Bovary’s eyes. I waited for my ride from the Book Fair for fifteen minutes in that dark alley before going to the locked door of the church and pounding and kicking until someone let me in and arranged to get me back to the hotel.

Future or no, there was no way I was going to walk through downtown Miami at night.

7.

My wife’s parents moved to Colorado from their home in Buffalo, New York, about five years ago. We drove back east with our five-year-old daughter to help them move that summer.

On the south side of Buffalo there is an old industrial section called Lackawanna. When the steel industry in this country went belly-up in the late ‘seventies and early ‘eighties, so did Lackawanna. Now one can drive on a pockmarked and decaying elevated highway through fifteen miles of abandoned steel plants, past weedgrown parking lots designed for five thousand vehicles but now empty except for a single watchman’s Pontiac, above slag heaps and scrap metal piles and blackened warehouses with broken windows. It goes on and on and on. The population of Buffalo is now little more than half of what it was twenty years ago. But the detritus remains.

“They should sell it to a movie company,” said my wife after ten minutes of driving through the rusting desolation, “and blow it up or something.”

“It’s been done,” I said. The air smelled of old ashes and something darker, more malignant.

8.

Both my parents suffered through radiation treatment: my mother for the brain tumor that killed her, my father for the lung cancer.

The effects of radiation and chemotherapy are—for much of the last months of a terminal patient’s life—more devastating than the cancer. We all know the signs: one’s hair falls out, blood pools under the skin, nausea and vomiting seem endless.

When I was a sixth-grade teacher, I taught a little girl who was undergoing such treatment. Cybele had been a ballerina before she got sick in fifth grade. She was still beautiful in sixth grade, although her skin was now so pale that it was translucent and she wore a kerchief on her head when she was in the world outside her family at home and her family of friends in the classroom. Her recovery from the brain tumor seemed almost miraculous, and by the summer after our year together she was beginning to dance again.

Cybele died in the spring of her seventh-grade year. The final months were terrible for her; she was in constant pain. She did not complain. Her ballet group specially choreographed The Nutcracker so that she could be Clara in the Christmas production and merely sit on the divan and watch the other dancers. When she died, the family did not use the services of a mortuary but held a simple ceremony at home. Cybele’s little brother and sister set special toys and photos and snacks in her coffin with her. Every day in sixth grade, my class would have “elevenses”—the British term for mid-morning snack—and every morning Cybele brought out her small brown bag of tortilla chips. Her mother and little brother Sammy set a small brown bag of tortilla chips next to her hand before she was buried.

9.

A friend of mine named Alan is a researcher for the National Center for Atmospheric Research in Boulder, and he was among the first to document the effects of chlorofluorocarbons on the ozone layer. As far back as the late ‘seventies he was flying above the arctic and antarctic in pressurized research aircraft, sampling the atmosphere and trying to guess at the extent of the damage.

One winter day not too many months ago, Alan and I were climbing on the Flatirons, a series of giant uptilted rock slabs rising above Boulder, when we climbed out of the Brown Cloud that lay over the Front Ridge like a blanket of airborne filth. Our heads actually came above the smog layer the way a swimmer suddenly rises above the surface of the water.

Eating our sandwiches and chips on a ledge high on the Flatirons, I asked Alan about his research. He said he had gone on to other things, leaving the ozone problem to satellites and statisticians.

“If I believed in the Gaia theory,” said Alan, “I’d say that the living organism that was the Earth is trying to save itself by treating its cancer with heavy doses of radiation.”

I swallowed the bit of sandwich I was chewing and raised an eyebrow. “And what’s the cancer?”

Alan smiled, leaned back against the warm limestone, and looked out at the Brown Cloud that stretched from Pikes Peak a hundred miles south to the Wyoming border a hundred miles north. “We are,” he said softly. “People. Us.”

I quit chewing. “And would that radiation treatment be in time?”

Alan shrugged and looked up at the traverse and final bit of climb ahead of us. “We’d better get going,” he said. “We don’t have too much time left before it gets dark.”

10.

Leaving Romania by the Orient Express, my sister-in-law and I spent a day in Budapest and took a hydrofoil up the Danube from there to Vienna. The boat ride was beautiful after the Stalinist nightmares of the train trip.

North of Hungary, between Komarno and the Czech city of Bratislava, those two countries are completing work on one of the largest and most idiotic engineering projects ever undertaken in Europe. A long series of massive dams, reservoirs, and canals are being connected to bypass the slow-moving Danube so that the river can be tapped for hydroelectric power. It will change the Danube and the surrounding countryside forever.

At a bend in the river called the Hungarian Gate, the Danube now irrigates eight nations of Europe, just as it has since before any of those countries existed. Looking at the tree-lined river and rustic valley from the hydrofoil, one can easily imagine the area as the frontier for the Roman Empire, with comfortable patrician dachas along the south bank and nothing but dark forests and barbarians to the north. The Dabcikovo and Dunakiliti Dams and the Gabcikovo Canal will end all that.

To realize a totalitarian fantasy hatched at the height of Stalinist excess, Hungary and Czechoslovakia will—with the help of Austrian bankers—dam the Danube, send the water down the fifteen-mile-long canal, destroy the floodplain habitats, silt the reservoirs so that the Danube Delta dies, pour more sewage than ever into the Danube, lower the water table to the point that entire forests far removed from the canal system will die, contaminate drinking water with heavy metals and industrial toxins, finish off the fish population, and drive untold species of wildfowl away from the area or into actual extinction. The Gabcikovo Canal, nearing completion, rises sixty-five feet above the surrounding plain and is built on an active earthquake fault. Any breech in the canal structure—much less in one of the shoddily-built dams—would send a tidal wave of destruction downriver to kill thousands of people and eradicate entire cities.

There is little organized resistance to the project. The Hungarians, who have much to lose and little to gain from the project, finally agreed to it after the energy shortages of the ‘seventies.

One additional benefit to the Czech government, and not a small one according to those who know, is that by diverting the Danube River almost a million ethnic Hungarians who now live north of the river in Czechslovakia (and who might someday want to reunite with Hungary) will wake up to find themselves on the south bank of a new moat that has replaced the ancient river. Czechoslovakia will be effectively “de-Magyarized,” an outcome which the Czech government has pursued since the days it was shipping Jews to German ovens.

There is little effective international opposition to Gabcikovo. Business is, after all, business. And national sovereignty rules everywhere. A planetary population that merely wrings its hands at the destruction of the rain forests will not focus on something as small as the destruction of the Danube and the life that has fed on it for millennia.

“It’s pretty,” said my sister-in-law as the hydrofoil skimmed its way past Esztergom and pounded northwest toward the Hungarian Gate.

I looked to the north bank. The forest stretched out to distant hills. The only sign of civilization was a wooden onion-dome church steeple miles to the north. Everything within our view would soon be submerged, dried up, or dead.

“Yes,” I said. “It’s pretty.” I went back to making notes about my Dracula horror-novel.

11.

My daughter’s birthday is on February 15. In Colorado, that date may bring summerlike weather or massive blizzards. When Jane turned six, the day was springlike, the sunlight warm. She wanted to go to the Denver Zoo and we did.

The Denver Zoo is old-fashioned and not terribly exciting, but it takes hours to see all of the sections. By early afternoon we had not made it to the primates yet and the day had turned cloudy and blustery.

“It’s getting cold, kiddo,” I said. “What do you say we call it a day and come back another time?”

Jane seemed to consider this. She was holding a black balloon with a zebra depicted on it in white stripes. “Can we stay and see the rest?” she said at last. “They might not all be here when we come back.”

We stayed and made the complete circuit.

12.

“How would you kill the cancer of humanity?” I asked my friend Bill. We were having lunch at the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Research Center in Boulder where Bill worked as an astrophysics instructor.

“If I were Gaia?” he asked around a mouthful of salad.

“Yeah.”

Bill looked at his fork. “I don’t much like the Gaia business,” he said. “It’s too limited. Too parochial.”

I gave him a quizzical look.

Bill sipped his iced tea and lifted the salad fork like a baton. “Why limit the self-regulation organism to just this planet?” he said.

“It’s the only one that has a biosphere,” I said.

He shrugged. “That’s like saying that the heart is the only muscle that pumps blood so that it’s the most important. Why not look at the system as the total self-regulating organism?”

I frowned. “The solar system?”

Bill picked a tomato out of the salad and ate it thoughtfully. “Why stop there? Assuming that super strings actually connect the galaxies on some level that we can’t understand and that the Taoist physicists are right that a cause here creates an effect there, why not designate the entire universe as Gaia?”

“All right,” I said. “Assuming that everything is Gaia and Gaia is everything, how would you go about eliminating the cancer of humanity?”

Bill focused on the blank cafeteria wall across from him.

“Well, assuming that Gaia was just the earth,” he began, ignoring the premise we had just created, “she’d have the usual selfregulating mechanisms for decreasing or eliminating the population: famine, disease . . . can’t say predators because we’ve eliminated almost all the other species that have traditionally preyed on us . . . except ourselves, of course.” He ran a hand through his mane of gray hair. “Ice ages, ozone depletion with its commensurate radiation rise, volcanic activity with its associated temperature drop, greenhouse effect with just the opposite effect . . .” He shook his head and looked at me. “Nope, none of them are radical enough to count as cancer surgery. Some might have the desired effect, but it takes too long. Like cancer, humanity metastasizes too quickly.”

“What if Gaia was the whole thing?” I said, gesturing feebly toward the ceiling.

Bill cleared his throat and adjusted his glasses. “Are we talking about Noah here?”

“No. Natural causes and believable effects.”

He rubbed his cheek. “Well, radiation is elegant. But it’s hard to get the desired amount from the sun. It’s too stable. Plus half the planet is shielded by the planet itself half the time.”

“Nova?” I said.

He shook his head. “Our sun can’t go nova. Too small by about a factor of ten.”

“A nearby sun then?” I persisted. “Supernova?”

Bill smiled as if I had finally said something interesting. “Most of my colleagues would get a hard-on if a nearby sun went supernova. Hasn’t happened in our galaxy since sixteen oh-four and the recording instruments weren’t too sophisticated then. Watching that sort of event in another galaxy’s sort of like kissing your sister . . .”

“But would it sterilize the cancer?” I said, realizing that I was perseverating.

Bill blinked and seemed to bring me in focus. “Kill all of us human germs?” he said. He pursed his lips for a minute and said, “Uh-uh.”

“Why not?”

He sighed the way any specialist sighs when he or she is talking to a not-especially-bright lay person. “Look, let’s say the nearest star to the earth . . . other than our own, of course . . . were to go supernova . . .”

“Alpha Centauri,” I said, trying to show him that I was not a total ignoramus.

Bill twitched a smile. “Proxima Centauri, yes. Let’s say it goes nova.”

“Supernova you mean.”

“No, just a plain nova to start with.” Bill looked down at the table and moved his fingers as if tapping invisible calculator keys. “It’d reach an absolute magnitude of about . . . mmm, nine . . . so that would give an apparent magnitude of . . . ah, thirteen point five let’s say. Pretty bright. About the same as a full moon. Of course, you couldn’t see it unless you were near the equator or in the southern hemisphere . . .”

“What about the radiation?” I asked calmly. I was determined not to show any impatience.

“You mean other than the visible radiation I just mentioned?” said Bill, matching my patience with his. “Hard radiation wouldn’t pose any problem, although there’d be some electromagnetic interference in communications bands using . . .”

“What about a supernova?” I interrupted.

Bill tapped the table again. “Okay. Not likely with the Centauri system, but let’s pretend . . . Mmmm, an absolute magnitude of twenty-one point five. Pretty bright. About four thousand full moons. You’d definitely cast a shadow. It’d be like a second, smaller sun in the sky for a couple of months. Like the end of that movie sequel, whatsitsname . . . Two Thousand Ten.”

I smiled a bit. “And it would wipe out humans? All the higher life forms?”

Bill matched my smile with a slight frown. “Did I say that? Uh-uh, the actual energy increase above what our sun puts out would be . . . oh, six tenths of a percent. Not insignificant, to be sure. It’d create havoc with our weather, wipe out satellite communication and keep the Concorde at lower altitudes for a few weeks, but wipe us out? No way.”

I must have looked disappointed, because Bill said, “But there is a way Gaia could eradicate us. Other than massive comet or meteor strikes, I mean . . . which seems like rather radical surgery since you’d have to wipe out all life down to the level of phytoplankton . . .”

“What?” I prompted after a moment of silence had passed.

“Triggering a supernova chain reaction,” he said, spearing at a radish in his salad.

I waited.

“Galaxy M-Eighty-two blew itself to shit about twelve million years ago,” said Bill. “There’s no reason ours couldn’t do it.” He pointed his fork at me. “You see, a lot of stars are already in the pre-supernova condition. A nearby supernova—this’d have to be near the Core obviously . . .”

“Obviously,” I said.

“A nearby supernova warms its pre-supernova neighbor that’s already on the brink of supernovadom and the radiation it absorbs shortens its already-short lifespan . . . say, from a thousand years before blowing to just a few months. Then star number two goes supernova and the energy of both blown stars travels a few light years—remember, this is in the Core—to a third pre-supernova sun and . . . well, it’s obvious . . .”

“Yes,” I said.

“A chain reaction like M Eighty-two,” he said, nodding.

I nodded with him.

“The release was equivalent to five or six million normal stars,” mused Bill, looking at the wall again. “We got pictures of the remnant of a hydrogen jet at least a thousand light-years long flashing out from the galaxy’s core. Like a giant blowtorch. Anything in the way of that torch got crisped. Then the entire galaxy blew like a kid’s balloon.”

I stared at him a moment. “So you’re saying that Gaia could get rid of humanity . . . the cancer . . . by blowing our entire galaxy to bits? Isn’t that a little extreme for a cure?”

Bill turned toward me. “Have you even seen the effects of a double mastectomy?”

I had. My mother had battled breast cancer before the brain tumor killed her. I remember standing in the upstairs hallway as a child of ten and seeing the light shining through her nightgown and thinking, Oh, Jesus.

“Besides,” said Bill, “there are over a hundred billion galaxies and each of them contain a couple of hundred billion stars on average. Don’t think of Earth . . . or even of our galaxy . . . as an organ in Gaia’s body. More of a cell.” He finished his iced tea, rose, and picked up his tray. “But then, I don’t buy this Gaia stuff anyway. See you around.”

I watched Bill amble away with his tray. There were no windows in the cafeteria. I had no idea if the sun was still out.

13.

Today, driving north along Interstate 25 toward Cheyenne, Wyoming, I count six cars with anti-nuclear bumper stickers. Our only nuclear power plant in Colorado is the St. Vrain Nuclear Power Station less than ten miles from my home. Designed as a

high-temperature gas-cooled reactor for regions with little water for coolant, the device was touted as infinitely safer than even the standard American water-cooled reactor, much less the type of insane, half-assed design that led to Chernobyl. But the St. Vrain reactor was a prototype and as expensive and cantankerous as a handbuilt Maserati. It was down for repairs more than it was on line. So the utility company cut its losses, shut the plant, and arranged to ship the radioactive core, the contaminated reactor vessel parts, and the tons of radioactive debris to the national storage center that had been planned for twenty years.

Only there is no national storage center. All of our western states refuse to accept nuclear waste, or the sites are not yet certified, or the political debate has stymied action. The waste sits there at St. Vrain Nuclear Power Station. Last summer two tornados ripped through the area, four miles from us, precisely between the reactor storage fields and our home.

Another car passes me. This bumper sticker says Split Wood, Not Atoms. Our area has over two hundred high-risk, pollution-alert, non-burn days a year. The mountain towns are worse. Vail and Aspen are literally strangling on their own wood smog.

The mountains seem to recede now and high prairie stretches miles to the west and a seemingly infinite distance to the east. Just before I reach the Wyoming border I see the Rawhide Energy Project in the middle of sagebrush and desolation. Its smokestacks seem taller than the mountains behind it. Rail lines cross the sagebrush-strewn prairie to deliver the mountains of coal the plant needs. There is little visible pollution today, but I know that the emissions from this plant follow the low area of the old Platte River and sometimes blanket the empty hearts of three western states with airborne particulates.

We are lucky here. In some areas, the high arsenic content of the coal being burned dumps over a ton and a half of arsenic a day on the surrounding countryside. School children in such areas test for almost lethal levels of arsenic in their hair, blood, and urine. Most do not immediately die from it. Many will die of cancer in years to come. Some of the children will receive radiation treatment, but that rarely works with a cancer that is sufficiently far along. I know. I have seen it.

The radio tells me that the President has again vetoed the findings of the international science committees that recommended immediate action to deal with the ozone depletion and the greenhouse effect. New committees will be convened to seek further data.

A green Ford Taurus passes me with a bumper sticker I have never seen before. It reads—CREATIVITY IS MORE IMPORTANT THAN KNOWLEDGE—Albert Einstein.

14.

Richard T. Chizmar is the guy who invited me to do an “ecological horror story.” I call him and tell him to forget it, that I have none to write.

15.

A group of us go backpacking into the Roosevelt National Forest along the Continental Divide. One of the guys has been foolish enough to pack two sixpacks of beers onto the eleven-thousand foot high sub-alpine plateau and we drink them all that first night.

I find myself telling my disjointed thoughts about Gaia. A friend of ours, a very smart but very New-Ageish woman named Niki, says, “You’ve got it all screwed up.”

I just look at her across the fire.

“We’re the cancer, all right,” she says, her dark eyes reflecting the flames, “but not because of all the overpopulation and pollution.”

“What then?” I say, mildly irritated. It was my theory.

“We’re the cancer because of all the emotional and psychic poisons we’re pouring into the world.”

I roll my eyes slightly and sip my beer. Niki has been to Sedona to tap into the power center there. If she and I have any common basis for conversation, we have not found it yet.

“I’m serious,” she says.

“You mean like bad vibes?” I say, trying not to let the derision be too audible.

She does not blink. “No,” she says. “I mean like hatred, like lust for power, like racism and anti-Semitism and the thousand other prejudices we pour into our surroundings every day of every year for thousands of years. If Gaia is real, then we’re destroying her mind and nervous system more surely than her other systems.”

“Mental illness,” says Connie.

“Madness,” says Tom.

“Didn’t the mercury in the tanning process used to drive hatters crazy?” says Karen from her place by the fallen tree. “Yep,” says Ed. “Thus the phrase ‘mad as a hatter.’ ”

Niki rests her elbows on her knees, laces her fingers, and stares into the campfire. “And what do people often do when they get crazy enough?”

“Kill themselves,” says Connie.

“Or other people first and then themselves,” says Tom.

A log comes apart and tumbles into the embers below, sending sparks rising toward the black sky.

16.

Distraught, ashamed, too deeply in debt to ever escape it, Emma Bovary went to the pharmacist’s house and gobbled arsenic. She vomited what looked like gravel into her basin at home. Then the pain began in earnest. She died horribly.

“Her chest immediately began to heave rapidly. Her whole tongue emerged from her mouth; her eyes rolled and grew dim, like the globes of two lamps about to go out, and she would have seemed dead already if it had not been for the frightful movement of her ribs, shaken by the furious, constantly quickening gasps, as though her soul were struggling to break away . . .

“Suddenly, from outside, came the sound of heavy wooden shoes and the scraping of a stick on the sidewalk, then a voice rose up, a raucous voice singing:

The heat of the sun on a summer day “Warms a young girl in an amorous way.

“Emma sat up like a galvanized corpse, her hair hanging loosely, her eyes fixed and gaping.

“To gather up the golden stalks

After the scythe has cut the wheat,

“Nanette bends down and slowly walks

Along the furrows at her feet.”

“The blind man!’ she cried.

“And she began to laugh, a horrible, frenzied, desperate laugh, imagining that she could see the wretched beggar’s hideous features looming in the shadows of eternity like the face of terror itself.

“The wind was blowing hard that day

And Nanette’s petticoat flew away.”

“A convulsion threw her back down on the mattress. Everyone moved toward her. She had ceased to exit.”

In my dream, Mother’s funeral is set among the slagheaps of Copsa Mica. The sky hangs low above us like black crepe. There are other mourners there. I see my brothers in the black-garbed throng, but I also see others whom I had not known were part of the family until today.

Mother is laid out on a black bier which itself lies upon a rusted mass of metal which may have once been a machine. When it is my turn, I step closer to pay my last respects. Her face is not as I remember it. For a second I think I have come to the wrong funeral or that they have replaced my mother’s body with a stranger’s, but then I see the familiar planes of the face and recognize the family resemblance. We all, in our silent rows, standing amidst the silent ashfall, we all resemble her.

Her mouth is open and is little more than a black hole at the bottom of her face. Her hands are contorted as if still fighting death. Her thumbs are bent inward. Her eyelids are congealed with faint granules, like spider eggs. Her eyes, which no one has closed, are beginning to disappear in a viscous pallor that is like a fine web.

I bend over to kiss her goodbye.

Mother’s eyes widen, air rushes from the hole of her mouth as if someone had leaned on a bellows, and her contorted fingers grasp my shoulders hard enough to snap bone and gristle. She pulls me toward her.

I think she is going to whisper something to me. I allow my ear and cheek to be drawn to her face.

A flood of black liquid vomits from her. Drenched in it, I try to pull away, but although her fingers have relinquished their grip on my shoulders, the black fluid is as sticky as tar. It connects me to the corpse like viscous strands of licorice-black muscle.

I can see the others inundated, struggling, webs of blackness connecting them to me, to her, and to each other. The ash is now falling so heavily that I cannot see faces, only black forms struggling in the ever-dimming gloom.

The voice, when it comes, is old and not kind. There is an offhand, almost taunting quality to it which belies the terrible struggle for existence going on in the sticky darkness all around me.

“Oh,” says the voice. “Look out for her dress!”

And then. “Give us a hand!”

The black fluid has covered my mouth and eyes by this time. I am holding my breath but know that in a second I must inhale the dark, gelatinous poison. It smells of oil and camphor and sulfur and arsenic and vomit. The voice when it comes an instant before I breathe in the blackness, is all but inaudible. “You’re not afraid, by any chance, are you?”